A Guide to the Recordings of the Virginia Supreme Court, 1969-2015
Library of Virginia
- Series I. Video recordings of court ceremonies,, 1991-2011., Extent: 23 video recordings.
  - Investiture of Barbara Milano Keenan as justice of the Virginia Supreme Court, 1991 July 2. (Box 1)
  - Investiture of Lawrence L. Koontz, Jr., as justice of the Virginia Supreme Court, 1995 August 16.
  - Investiture of Cynthia Fannon Kinser as justice of the Virginia Supreme Court, 1997 July 8.
  - Ceremony honoring Chief Justice Harry L. Carrico upon his retirement from full-time service, 2003 January 1.
  - Investiture of Justice Leroy R. Hassell, Sr., as Chief Justice of the Virginia Supreme Court, 2003 February 11.
  - Swearing-in ceremony of Justice Leroy R. Hassell, Sr., as Chief Justice of the Virginia Supreme Court, 2003 February 11.
  - Investiture of G. Steven Agee as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2003 March 5.
  - Ceremony honoring David Beach upon his retirement from the position of Clerk, Supreme Court of Virginia, 2003 June 1.
  - Ceremony commemorating the 225th anniversary of the establishment of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2004 December 9.
  - Ceremony honoring Robert N. Baldwin upon his retirement from the position of Executive Secretary, Supreme Court of Virginia, 2005 March 31.
  - Portrait presentation ceremony honoring Harry L. Carrico, A. Christian Compton, Roscoe B. Stephenson, and Charles Russell, 2006 February 28.
  - Ceremony commemorating the 230th anniversary of the enactment of Virginia's first constitution, 2006 November 2.
  - Swearing-in ceremony of S. Bernard Goodwyn as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2007 October 10.
  - Investiture of LeRoy F. Millette as judge on the Court of Appeals of Virginia, 2008 February 22.
  - Investiture of LeRoy F. Millette as justice on the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2008 September 5.
  - Investiture of Cleo Elaine Powell as judge of the Court of Appeals of Virginia, 2008 November 17.
  - Investiture of William C. Mims as justice on the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2010 April 9.
  - Investiture of Justice Cynthia D. F. Kinser as Chief Justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2011 February 16.
  - Investiture of Elizabeth A. McClanahan as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2011 September 1.
- Series II. Miscellanous court video recordings,, XX., Extent: XX video recordings.
  Miscellaneous court video recordings include various presentations and speeches.
  - XX, XX.
- Series III. Audio recordings of court ceremonies,, 1969-2005., Extent: 18 digital audio recordings.
  This series contains audio recordings of Supreme Court of Virginia ceremonies, 1969-2005; and Court of Appeals of Virginia ceremonies, 1985-1989. The ceremonies took place in the courtrooms of the Supreme Court of Virginia and the Court of Appeals of Virginia in Richmond.
  The Supreme Court ceremonies include investiture and portrait presentation ceremonies, 1969-1985; the bicentennial of the court, 1979; and the dedication of the Supreme Court Building, 1981. Investitures includ of those of Justice John Charles Thomas, the first African-American justice of the court, in 1983, and Justice Elizabeth B. Lacy, the first female justice on the court, in 1989.
  This series also contain recordings of three Court of Appeals of Virginia ceremnonies: the swearing-in ceremony of the first court, 1985; the swearing-in ceremony for Judge Jere M.H. Willis, Jr., 1989; and the portrait presentation for E. Ballard Baker, first Chief Judge, 1985.
  This series includes the following audio files:
  Investitures of George M. Cochran and Alexander M. Harmon as justices of the Supreme Court of Virginia and swearing-in of Justice Harold Snead as Chief Justice, 1969 October 1 (24 minutes). Remarks by Justice W. I'Anson honoring Chief Justice Snead; Chief Justice Snead, presiding over investitures; remarks by Howard C. Gilmer, Harmon's former law partner.
  Investiture of Richard H. Poff as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 1972 August 30 (11 minutes, 49 seconds). Chief Justice Harold Snead, presiding; remarks by former Governor William M. Tuck and the Hon. Lewis F. Powell, Associate Justice, U.S. Supreme Court.
  Ceremony commemorating the bicentennial of the founding of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 1979 August 30 (29 minutes). Chief Justice Lawrence W. I'Anson, presiding; remarks by Governor John Dalton; Chief Justice I'Anson; and U.S. Supreme Court Justice Lewis Powell, Jr., read by his son Lewis Powell, III. The ceremony includes the presentation of the portrait of Henry Tazewell, who served on the court from 1785 to 1788 and 1793 to 1794. A transcript of the ceremony is published in 220 Virginia Reports, p. ix.
  Portrait presentation for Supreme Court of Virginia Justice Archibald B. Buchanan, 1980 April 17 (14 minutes, 22 seconds). Chief Justice I'Anson, presiding; remarks by Justice Alexander Harmon. A transcript of the ceremony is published in 223 Virginia Reports, p. xi.
  Investiture of Roscoe B. Stephenson as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 1981 March 2 (23 minutes). Chief Justice Harry L. Carrico, presiding; remarks by William S. Moffatt, Chief Judge, 25th Judicial Circuit; presentation of resolutions honoring Stephenson.
  Dedication of the Supreme Court of Virginia Building, 1981 Dec 4 (35 minutes, 18 seconds). Chief Justice Harry L. Carrico, presiding; remarks by Delegate George Allen, Jr.; State Senator Edward E. Willey; Governor John Dalton; and Chief Justice Carrico.
  Portrait presentation for retired Supreme Court of Virginia Chief Justice Harold Snead, 1982 June 16 (50 minutes, 38 seconds). Chief Justice Harry L. Carrico, presiding; remarks by William B. Poff; former Chief Justice Lawrence W. I'Anson; and Governor Charles S. Robb. A transcript of the ceremony in published in 223 Virginia Reports, p. xix.
  Investiture of John Charles Thomas as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 1983 April 25 (34 minutes, 28 seconds). Chief Justice Harry L. Carrico, presiding; remarks by Governor Charles S. Robb; T.S. Ellis, III; Dennis C. Montgomery; and Justice Thomas; presentation of resolutions honoring Thomas. John Charles Thomas was the first African-American to serve on the Supreme Court of Virginia.
  Portrait presentation for retired Supreme Court of Virginia Chief Justice Lawrence W. I'Anson, 1983 June 15 (45 minutes, 14 seconds). Chief Justice Harry L. Carrico, presiding; remarks by Governor John Dalton; Virginia Senator Edward E. Willey; former Governor Mills E. Godwin; and others. A transcript of the ceremony is published in 225 Virginia Reports, p. vii.
  Swearing-in ceremony for the first judges on the Court of Appeals of Virginia, 1985 January 4 (30 minutes, 4 seconds). Chief Judge E. Ballard Baker, presiding; remarks by William D. Dolan, III, President of the Virginia State Bar; Harry L. Carrico, Chief Justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia; Edward Willey, President Pro Tempore, Senate of Virginia; Delegate Theodore V. Marsden, Jr.; and Governor Charles S. Robb.
  Swearing-in ceremony for Elizabeth B. Lacy, Judge, State Corporation Commission, 1985 April 1 (18 minutes). Harry L. Carrico, Chief Justice Supreme Court, Supreme Court of Virginia, presiding; remarks by Governor Charles S. Robb; Judge Thomas P. Harwood, Jr., member, State Corporation Commission; Commissioner Lacy; and Attorney General Gerald S. Baliles. Commission read by G. Patrick Lacy.
  Portrait presentation for E. Ballard Baker, first Chief Judge, Court of Appeals of Virginia, 1986 May 5 (19 minutes). Chief Judge Lawrence Koontz, presiding; remarks by Chief Judge Koontz; Governor Gerald L. Baliles; Harry L. Carrico, Chief Justice, Supreme Court of Virginia; James C. Roberts, Past President of the Virginia State Bar; and Billy Jane Baker, widow of Judge Baker.
  Investiture of Elizabeth B. Lacy as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 1989 January 4 (25 minutes, 52 seconds). Chief Justice Harry L. Carrico, presiding; invocation and benediction by William G. Broaddus; remarks by Governor Gerald L. Balilies and Justice Lacy; presentation of resolutions honoring Lacy. Elizabeth B. Lacy was the first woman to serve on the Supreme Court of Virginia.
  Portrait presentation for retired Supreme Court Justice George M. Cochran, 1989 April 20 (50 minutes). Chief Justice Harry L. Carrico, presiding; remarks by former Governor and retired justice Albertis S. Harrison; former Governor Mills E. Godwin; retired Chief Justice Lawrence W. I'Anson; and others. A transcript of the ceremony is published in 238 Virginia Reports, p. ix.
  Swearing-in ceremony for Jere H. Willis as Judge, Court of Appeals of Virginia, and recognition of the service of retiring Judge William H. Hodges, 1989 October 26 (22 minutes, 4 seconds, partially inaudible). Chief Judge Koontz, presiding.
  Investiture of Leroy Rountree Hassell, Sr., as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 1989 Dec 28 (26 minutes, 30 seconds). Chief Justice Harry L. Carrico, presiding; remarks by Governor Gerald L. Baliles and Justice Hassell; presentation of resolutions honoring Hassell.
  Investiture of Donald W. Lemons as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2000 April 3 (45 minutes). Chief Justice Harry L. Carrico, presiding; remarks by State Senator Walter Stosch; Governor James S. Gilmore; and Justice Lemons; presentation of resolutions honoring Lemons.
  Portrait presentation for Supreme Court Justices Richard H. Poff, W. Carrington Thompson and Henry Hudson Whiting, 2005 November 1 (11 minutes, 37 seconds). Chief Justice Leroy Hassell, presiding. A transcript of the ceremony is published in 271 Virginia Reports, p. ix.
  - Investitures of George M. Cochran and Alexander M. Harman as justices of the Supreme Court of Virginia and swearing-in of Justice Harold Snead as Chief Justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 1969 Oct q. (Box X)
  - Investiture of Richard H. Poff as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 1972 Aug 30. (Box X)
  - Ceremony commemorating the bicentennial of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 1979 Aug 30. (Box X)
  - Portrait presentation for Supreme Court of Virginia Justice Archibald B. Buchanan, 1980 Apr 17. (Box X)
  - Investiture of Roscoe B. Stephenson as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 1981 Mar 2. (Box X)
  - Dedication of the Supreme Court of Virginia Building, 1981 Dec 4. (Box X)
  - Portrait presentation for retired Supreme Court of Virginia Chief Justice Harold Snead, 1982 June 16. (Box X)
  - Investiture of John Charles Thomas as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 1983 Apr 25. (Box X)
  - Portrait presentation for retired Supreme Court of Virginia Lawrence W. I'Anson, 1983 June 15. (Box X)
  - Swearing-in ceremony for the first judges on the Court of Appeals of Virginia, 1985 Jan 4. (Box X)
  - Swearing-in ceremony for Elizabeth B. Lacy, Judge, State Corportion Commission, 1985 Apr 1. (Box X)
  - Portrait presentation for E. Baker Ballard, first Chief Judge, Court of Appeals of Virginia, 1986 May 5. (Box X)
  - Investiture of Elizabeth B. Lacy as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 1989 Jan 4. (Box X)
  - Portrait presentation for retired Supreme Court George M. Cochran, 1989 Apr 20. (Box X)
  - Swearing-in ceremony for Jere H. Willis as Judge, Court of Appeals of Virginia, and recognition of the service of retiring Judge William H. Hodges, 1989 Oct 16. (Box X)
  - Investiture of Leroy Rountree Hassell, Sr., as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 1989 Dec 28. (Box X)
  - Investiture of Donald W. Lemons as justice of the Supreme Court of Virginia, 2000 Apr 3. (Box X)
  - Portrait presentation for Supreme Court Justices Richard H. Poff, W. Carrington Thompson, and Henry Hudson Whiting, 2005 Nov 1. (Box X)
- Series IV. Video recordings of Supreme Court Oral History Interviews,, 2007-2015., Extent: 8 video recordings.
  This series includes 8 video recordings of oral history interviews with retired Supreme Court of Virginia justices. The interviews were conducted for the Supreme Court of Virginia Historical Commission beginning in 2007. The Supreme Court of Virginia Historical Advisory Committee (formerly Commission) was established in 2006 to preserve and promote the history of the court. Oral history interviews of retired Supreme Court justices, Court of Appeals judges, other individuals associated with the court, and civil rights attorneys were begun in 2007 and the project is ongoing.
  Includes the following oral history interviews:
  Oral history interview with Justice Harry L. Carrico by Arlington County Circuit Court Judge Joanne Alper, 2007 April 12 (78 minutes, transcript available at the Supreme Court of Virginia). Justice Carrico discusses changes he witnessed during his long tenure on the court, his experiences as a young lawyer and judge in northern Virginia (Alexandria, and Fairfax and Prince William counties) in the 1940s and 1950s, his work on the Judicial Conference of the U.S. and his relationships with U.S. Supreme Court Justices Warren Burger and William Rehnquist. Toward the end of the interview, he reflects on his relationships with the justices of the Supreme Court of Virginia when he was appointed in 1961, his workflow and opinion-writing process, the creation of the Office of the Executive Secretary (court administrator), and the appointments of the first African American and women justices to the court.
  Oral history interview with Justice Harry L. Carrico by Norfolk State Professor of History Cassandra Newby-Alexander, 2007 November 8 (1 hour, 57 minutes; transcript available at the Supreme Court of Virginia). Justice Carrico discusses his family and early life on a dairy farm in rural Fairfax County, his father's work as a billboard artist for the General Outdoor Advertising Company and his business operating a riding stable. He recalls going to a combined grade school and high school in Bailey's Crossroads and attending Lee-Jackson High School in Fairfax County, and working and attending law school in Washington, D.C. He discusses his experience working in contract terminations in the Navy during world War II, his work as a lawyer and judge in Fairfax County before and after the war, and his appointment to the Supreme Court of Virginia 1961. Toward the end of the interview, Carrico talks about the process of writing opinions, and his decision in Loving v. Commonwealth of Virginia, which upheld the state statute barring interracial marriage in 1967. He reflects on the changes in the court during his tenure, including the appointment of the first African American and women justices, and his recollections of the justices who were on the court when he was appointed in 1961 (Chief Justice John Eggleston, Justice L. Warren I'Anson, Justice Claude V. Spratley, Justice Harold S. Snead). The interview ends with a discussion of Carrico's work for the John Marshall Foundation and his thoughts about the historical importance of Marshall's contributions to the judiciary.
  Oral history interview with Justice George M. Cochran by Norfolk State Professor of History Cassandra Newby-Alexander, 2007 March 30 (1 hour, 56 minutes; transcript available at the Supreme Court of Virginia). Justice Cochran talks about his family's roots in Staunton, his ancestor Alexander H.H. Stuart and Stuart's political career before and after the Civil War. He reflects on his early life in Staunton, his education at Episcopal High School in Alexandria and at the University of Virginia, and his service in the navy in California and the Pacific during World War II. He discusses being a state legislator during the 1950s and 1960s and efforts by a younger general of legislators to repeal the poll tax and segregation laws after World War II. Cochran also reflects on Massive Resistance and working to establish a community college system in Virginia. He talks about working with fellow state legislators Armistead Booth, Mosby G. Perrow, Tayloe Murphy, Mills Godwin and Albertis Harrison, and Governor Colgate Darden and Governor Lindsay Almond. Toward the end of the interview, Cochran talks about his appointment to the Supreme Court of Virginia, his friendship with Albertis Harrison when they were both on the court, his thoughts about dissenting from the majority, and making the transition from writing legal briefs to writing judicial opinions. The interview concludes with Cochran's recollections about organizing meetings of the Virginia State Bar Association in England and Scotland, the appointment of the first African Ameerican and women justices to the court, and socializing with other out-of-town justices at the John Marshall Hotel in Richmond.
  Oral history interview with Judge Barbara Milano Keenan by Norfolk State Professor of History Cassandra Newby-Alexander, 2013 June 6 (2 hours, 38 minutes; transcript available at the Supreme Court of Virginia). Judge Keenan talks about her family's history and the influence of their experiences as immigrants in West Virginia in the early twentieth century, attending Catholic high school in Arlington, Virginia, and college at Cornell University during the 1960s; and working at the U.S. Department of Justice while attending Law School at George Washington University. She discusses her early career as an assistant commonwealth's attorney in Fairfax, and her service on the Court of Appeals of Virginia, the Supreme Court of Virginia and the Fourth Circuit, U.S. Court of Appeals. She also reflects on the experience of being among the first women judges in Virginia and the influences of mentors and colleagues throughout her career.
  Oral history interview with Justice Lawrence L. Koontz, Jr., by Gail Warren, State Law Librarian, 2013 May 17 (55 minutes; transcript available at the Supreme Court of Virginia). Justice Koontz talks about growing up in Salem, Virginia, attending Virginia Tech and law school at the University of Richmond, and his early years as a lawyer, commonwealth's attorney, and judge in Roanoke. He reflects on the experience of forming rules and procedures for the Court of Appeals of Virginia, serving on the Supreme Court of Virginia, and changes in the legal profession and the judiciary during his career.
  Oral history interview with Justice Elizabeth B. Lacy by Norfolk State Professor of History Cassandra Newby-Alexander, 2008 Sept 15 (1 hour, 56 minutes; transcript available at the Supreme Court of Virginia). Justice Lacy talks about growing up in Oshkosh, Wisconsin, where her parents owned a business in the 1950s; her education at Catholic schools in Oshkosh and St. Mary's College at Notre Dame; and attending law school at the University of Texas in Austin. She talks about her early legal career working for the Texas Legislative Council and the Texas Attorney General's office, where she became the first woman division chief. She reflects on the political atmosphere in Texas when she was in law school and in the early years of her legal career, and the influence of women such as Barbara Jordan, Kay Bailey Hutchinson, Sarah Weddinton, and others who were elected to public office in Texas in the late 1960s and early 1970s. In the second part of the interview, Justice Lacy recounts moving to Virginia in the late 1970s, her work as Deputy Attorney General under Attorney General Gerald Baliles, her appointment to the State Corporation Commission in 1985 and her work there, and her subsequent appointment to the Supreme Court of Virginia in 1989. The interview ends with Lacy's reflections on her early experiences on the court and changes in the court during her tenure.
  Oral history interview with Justice Charles S. Russell by Arlington County Circuit Court Judge Joanne Alper, 2007 April 23 (1 hour, 8 minutes; transcript available at the Supreme Court of Virginia). Justice Russell talks about his experience as a circuit court judge in Arlington County and his tenure on the Supreme Court of Virginia. He discusses his election to the court by one vote in 1982 and reflects on the changes in the Virginia judiciary during his tenure as a justice, particularly a greater acceptance of dissent and declining deference toward older justices. Russell also talks about the colorful personalities he remembers from his early years as a member of the Arlington County bar. Russell also reflects on memorable cases and historical events during his career. The interview closes with Russell's recollection of watching the attack on the Pentagon from his office window in Arlington in Arlington on September 11, 2001, and his thoughts about the lasting impact of the event.
  Oral history interview with Justice Roscoe B. Stephenson by Norfolk State Professor of History Cassandra Newby-Alexander, 2007 Apr 30 (1 hour, 27 minutes; transcript available at the Supreme Court of Virginia). Justice Stephenson talks about his parents and siblings and growing up in Covington, Virginia, where his father was a lawyer. He recalls attending Washingtong and Lee University as an undergraduate and working on a construction project in Hampton and a steamer out of Baltimore during the break between college and law school after he was discharged from the army on account of aheart murmer. Stephenson recalls that he was only one of two students attending law school at Washington and Lee University in 1945 because of World War II. He talks of returning to Covington after law school, practicing law there with his father in the 1950s, and being Commonwealth's Attorney and circuit court judge in Alleghany County. Stephenson reflects on changes in the judiciary beginning in the 1970s, particularly the increase of women in the profession and the appointment of Elizabeth Lacy to the court as the first female justice in 1989. In the second part of the interview, Stephenson talks about his approach to writing opinions and about cases that were particularly memorable. He discusses the use of DNA evidence in the Spencer v. Commonwealth case, other death penalty cases, and cases involving the rights to mine coal and gas. The interview closes with Stephenson's recollections of his relationships with other justices and law clerks, and memories of socializing with out-of-town justices at the John Marshall Hotel in Richmond when the court was in session.
  Oral history interview with Justice John Charles Thomas by Norfolk State Professor of History Cassandra Newby-Alexander, 2007 Aug 8 (2 hours, 21 minutes; transcript avaialable at the Supreme Court of Virginia). Justice Thomas discusses his family's roots in the Huntersville neighborhood of Norfolk, growing up in segregated Norfolk, and the influence on him of his parents, grandparents, extended family, community, school and church. He recalls his maternal grandfather, who taught him to recite poetry when he was a young boy, and the minister of the First Baptist Church. He talks about his decision to attend Maury High School, a predominately white high school in Norfolk, in 1965, and his experiences as a student there; and attending the University of Virginia. Thomas also reflects on clerking for the Civil Right Division of the Justice Department one summer when he was a law student, and how this experience helped him in his efforts to secure a position at a large law firm in Virginia after he graduated. He recounts his early years working at the Richmond law firm Hunton and Williams, where he did legal work for Virginia Electric and Power Company, and becoming the first African American lawyer to make partner at a white law firm in the South. Toward the end of the interview, Justice Thomas discusses his appointment fo the Supreme Court of Virginia and being the first African American appointed to the court. He reflects on differneces between himself and the other justices, in style, training and age. The interview closes with Thomas' thoughts on memorable opinions.